channels	channels
Manual 	マニュアル
Standard library 	標準ライブラリ
Index 	インデックス
Search:  	検索：
Group by:  	分類:
Section 	セクション
Type 	型
Example 	用例
Sample output 	出力例
Passing Channels Safely 	チャネルの安全な渡しかた
Types 	型
Channel 	Channel 
Procs 	プロシージャ
send 	send 
trySend 	trySend 
recv 	recv 
tryRecv 	tryRecv 
peek 	peek 
open 	open 
close 	close
ready 	ready 
Channel support for threads.	Channels はスレッドをサポートしています。
Note: This is part of the system module.	これは system モジュールの一部です。
Do not import it directly.	明示的にインポートしないでください。
To activate thread support compile with the --threads:on command line switch.	スレッドのサポートを有効にするにはコマンドラインスイッチ --threads をつけてコンパイルしてください。
Note: Channels are designed for the Thread type.	備考: Channels は Thread 型として設計してあります。 
They are unstable when used with spawn	spawn との併用時は動作が不安定になります。
Note: The current implementation of message passing does not work with cyclic data structures.	備考: 現在のメッセージパッシングにおける実装では循環データ構造は動作しません。
Note: Channels cannot be passed between threads.	備考: Channels はスレッド間での受け渡しはできません。
Use globals or pass them by ptr.	グローバル変数 (globals)、または ptr 渡しをお使いください。
Example	用例
The following is a simple example of two different ways to use channels: blocking and non-blocking.	このサンプルはチャンネルの二通りの使い方を記したものです: ブロッキングとノンブロッキングです。
# Be sure to compile with --threads:on.	# 必ず --threads:on でコンパイルすることをお忘れなく。
# The channels and threads modules are part of system and should not be # imported.	# channels モジュールと threads モジュールは system  # モジュールの一部であるためインポートしないでください。
import os	import os
# Channels can either be:	# いずれかの方法でチャンネルを使えます:
#  - declared at the module level, or	# ・モジュールレベルでの宣言、
#  - passed to procedures by ptr (raw pointer) -- see note on safety.	# ・または ptr によるプロシージャ渡し (生ポインタ) － 安全性については注釈を参照してください。
# # For simplicity, in this example a channel is declared at module scope.	# 簡潔にするために、この用例ではモジュールのスコープでチャンネルを宣言しています。
# Channels are generic, and they include support for passing objects between # threads.	# チャンネルは一般的なものであり、チャンネル間での # オブジェクト渡しに関するサポートもあります。
# Note that objects passed through channels will be deeply copied.	# スレッドを通じて渡されたオブジェクトはディープコピーされることに注意してください。
var chan: Channel[string]	var chan: Channel[string]
# This proc will be run in another thread using the threads module.	# ここでは threads モジュールを用いて、別のプロシージャを別のスレッドで実行します。
proc firstWorker() =   chan.send("Hello World!")	proc firstWorker() =   chan.send("Hello World!")
# This is another proc to run in a background thread.	# ここでは別のプロシージャをバックグラウンドで実行します。
This proc takes a while # to send the message since it sleeps for 2 seconds (or 2000 milliseconds).	# このプロシージャはメッセージの送信で 2 秒間 (2000ミリ秒) の休止をします。
proc secondWorker() =   sleep(2000)   chan.send("Another message")	proc secondWorker() =   sleep(2000)   chan.send("Another message")
# Initialize the channel.	# チャンネルの初期化。
chan.open()	chan.open()
# Launch the worker.	# ワーカーを起動します。
var worker1: Thread[void] createThread(worker1, firstWorker)	var worker1: Thread[void] createThread(worker1, firstWorker)
# Block until the message arrives, then print it out.	# メッセージが到着するまでブロックを行い、到着後に出力表示をします。
echo chan.recv() # "Hello World!"	echo chan.recv() # "Hello World!"
# Wait for the thread to exit before moving on to the next example.	# 次の用例へ移動する前に第二スレッドの終了を待機します。
worker1.joinThread()	worker1.joinThread()
# Launch the other worker.	# ほかのワーカーを起動します。
var worker2: Thread[void] createThread(worker2, secondWorker)	var worker2: Thread[void] createThread(worker2, secondWorker)
# This time, use a non-blocking approach with tryRecv.	# 今回は tryRecv でノンブロッキング手法を使います。
# Since the main thread is not blocked, it could be used to perform other # useful work while it waits for data to arrive on the channel.	# データがチャンネルに到着するのを待機する間は # メインスレッドはブロックされないため、ほかの有用な作業をするために使えます。
while true:   let tried = chan.tryRecv()   if tried.dataAvailable:     echo tried.msg # "Another message"     break      echo "Pretend I'm doing useful work..."	while true:   let tried = chan.tryRecv()   if tried.dataAvailable:     echo tried.msg # "Another message"     break      echo "Pretend I'm doing useful work..."
# For this example, sleep in order not to flood stdout with the above message.	# この用例では、上述のメッセージを stdout で溢れさせないために休止処理をします。
#  sleep(400)	#  sleep(400)
# Wait for the second thread to exit before cleaning up the channel.	# チャンネルのクリーンアップ前に第二スレッドの終了を待機します。
worker2.joinThread()	worker2.joinThread()
# Clean up the channel.	# チャンネルのクリーンアップ。
chan.close()	chan.close()
Sample output	出力例
The program should output something similar to this, but keep in mind that exact results may vary in the real world:	この結果と同じものをプログラムで出力しますが、想定している正確な結果と実際の結果は異なる場合があることをお断りしておきます。
Hello World!	Hello World!
Pretend I'm doing useful work...	Pretend I'm doing useful work...
Pretend I'm doing useful work...	Pretend I'm doing useful work...
Pretend I'm doing useful work...	Pretend I'm doing useful work...
Pretend I'm doing useful work...	Pretend I'm doing useful work...
Pretend I'm doing useful work...	Pretend I'm doing useful work...
Another message	Another message
Passing Channels Safely	チャネルの安全な渡しかた
Note that when passing objects to procedures on another thread by pointer (for example through a thread's argument), objects created using the default allocator will use thread-local, GC-managed memory.	ポインタにより別スレッドにあるプロシージャへオブジェクトを渡すときは (例えばスレッドの引数を通じて)、デフォルトのアロケータで作成されたオブジェクトはスレッド・ローカルのガベージコレクタにより管理されたメモリを使うことに注意してください。
Thus it is generally safer to store channel objects in global variables (as in the above example), in which case they will use a process-wide (thread-safe) shared heap.	従って、一般には channel オブジェクトをグローバル変数へ格納するほうが安全であり (上述の用例など)、いずれの場合であってもプロセス広域 (スレッドセーフ) の共有ヒープを使います。
However, it is possible to manually allocate shared memory for channels using e.g. system.allocShared0 and pass these pointers through thread arguments:	しかし、 system.allocShared0 などを用いて channels の共有メモリを手動で割り当てることでスレッドの引数としてポインタを渡すことは可能です。
proc worker(channel: ptr Channel[string]) =   let greeting = channel[].recv()   echo greeting  proc localChannelExample() =	proc worker(channel: ptr Channel[string]) =   let greeting = channel[].recv()   echo greeting  proc localChannelExample() =
# Use allocShared0 to allocate some shared-heap memory and zero it.	# allocShared0 を使うと共有ヒープの割り当てとゼロクリアを行います。
# The usual warnings about dealing with raw pointers apply. Exercise caution.	# 通常、生ポインタを扱うと警告が発生します。ご用事を。
var channel = cast[ptr Channel[string]](     allocShared0(sizeof(Channel[string]))   )   channel[].open()	var channel = cast[ptr Channel[string]](     allocShared0(sizeof(Channel[string]))   )   channel[].open()
# Create a thread which will receive the channel as an argument.	# 引数としてチャンネルを得るスレッドを作成します。
var thread: Thread[ptr Channel[string]]   createThread(thread, worker, channel)   channel[].send("Hello from the main thread!")	var thread: Thread[ptr Channel[string]]   createThread(thread, worker, channel)   channel[].send("Hello from the main thread!")
# Clean up resources.	# リソースのクリーンアップ。
thread.joinThread()   channel[].close()   deallocShared(channel)	thread.joinThread()   channel[].close()   deallocShared(channel)
localChannelExample() # "Hello from the main thread!"	localChannelExample() # "メインスレッドから Hello!"
Types	型
Channel*[TMsg] {...}{.gcsafe.} = RawChannel	Channel*[TMsg] {...}{.gcsafe.} = RawChannel
a channel for thread communication   	スレッド通信用チャンネルです。
Source Edit 	ソース 編集
Procs	プロシージャ
proc send*[TMsg](c: var Channel[TMsg]; msg: TMsg) {...}{.inline.}	proc send*[TMsg](c: var Channel[TMsg]; msg: TMsg) {...}{.inline.}
Sends a message to a thread. msg is deeply copied.	スレッドへメッセージを送信します。 msg はディープコピーされます。
Source Edit 	ソース 編集
proc trySend*[TMsg](c: var Channel[TMsg]; msg: TMsg): bool {...}{.inline.}	proc trySend*[TMsg](c: var Channel[TMsg]; msg: TMsg): bool {...}{.inline.}
Tries to send a message to a thread.	スレッドへメッセージの送信を試行します。
msg is deeply copied.	msg はディープコピーされます。
Doesn't block.	ブロックはできません。
Returns false if the message was not sent because number of pending items in the channel exceeded maxItems.	チャンネルで保留中のアイテム件数が maxItems を超過してしまい、メッセージの送信ができないときは false を返します。
Source Edit 	ソース 編集
proc recv*[TMsg](c: var Channel[TMsg]): TMsg	proc recv*[TMsg](c: var Channel[TMsg]): TMsg
Receives a message from the channel c.	チャンネル c からメッセージを受信します。
This blocks until a message has arrived!	メッセージの着信があるまでブロックします！
You may use peek proc to avoid the blocking.	ブロックを回避するには peek プロシージャをお使いください。
Source Edit 	ソース 編集
proc tryRecv*[TMsg](c: var Channel[TMsg]): tuple[dataAvailable: bool, msg: TMsg]	proc tryRecv*[TMsg](c: var Channel[TMsg]): tuple[dataAvailable: bool, msg: TMsg]
Tries to receive a message from the channel c, but this can fail for all sort of reasons, including contention.	チャンネル c からメッセージの受信を試行しますが、競合など様々な要因で失敗することがあります。
If it fails, it returns (false, default(msg)) otherwise it returns (true, msg).	失敗時は (false, default(msg)) を、それ以外は (true, msg) を返します。
Source Edit 	ソース 編集
proc peek*[TMsg](c: var Channel[TMsg]): int	proc peek*[TMsg](c: var Channel[TMsg]): int
Returns the current number of messages in the channel c.	チャンネル c における現在のメッセージ件数を返します。
Returns -1 if the channel has been closed.	チャンネルが閉じられているときは -1 を返します。
Note: This is dangerous to use as it encourages races.	注意: このプロシージャは競合の助長となるため危険です。
It's much better to use tryRecv proc instead.	よって tryRecv プロシージャの使用をお勧めします。
Source Edit 	ソース 編集
proc open*[TMsg](c: var Channel[TMsg]; maxItems: int = 0)	proc open*[TMsg](c: var Channel[TMsg]; maxItems: int = 0)
Opens a channel c for inter thread communication.	スレッド間通信用のチャンネル c を開きます。
The send operation will block until number of unprocessed items is less than maxItems.	未処理アイテム件数が maxItems 以下になるまで send 処理をブロックします。
For unlimited queue set maxItems to 0.	キューを無制限にするには maxItems に 0を設定します。
Source Edit 	ソース 編集
proc close*[TMsg](c: var Channel[TMsg])	proc close*[TMsg](c: var Channel[TMsg])
Closes a channel c and frees its associated resources.	チャンネルを閉じて関連リソースを開放します。
Source Edit 	ソース 編集
proc ready*[TMsg](c: var Channel[TMsg]): bool	proc ready*[TMsg](c: var Channel[TMsg]): bool
Returns true iff some thread is waiting on the channel c for new messages.	スレッドにおいてチャンネル c で新着メッセージを待機している場合に限り trueを返します。
Source Edit 	ソース 編集
Made with Nim.	Nim で作成しました。
Generated: 2020-01-23 17:27:14 UTC 	生成日時: 2020年01月23日 午前17時27分17秒 (UTC)
